## Saul Ortigoza

# Sr. Staff Cloud Architect / Site Reliability Engineer / DevOps / Engineering Manager

Experienced technology leader with a demonstrated history of working in software development and cloud computing. Proficient in a variety of languages, tools, and practices.

Cloud (7+ years): AWS, GCP

Containers (7+ years): Kubernetes, Docker

**Practices (8+ years):** CI/CD, DevOps, QA, Serverless **Tools (7+ years):** Terraform, Jenkins, Ansible, Automation

Languages: Python (10+ years), Ruby (4+ years), Golang (2+ years), Java, JavaScript

Soft Skills: Critical Thinking, Leadership, Strategy

Email: sortigoza.jobs@gmail.com

Twitter: @saul\_ortigoza
GitHub: @sortigoza
LinkedIn: saul-ortigoza
Resume: PDF Link

## **Certifications**

- Amazon Web Services: Solutions Architect Professional (Certified)
- ISTQB Advanced Test Analyst Level (Certified)

## **Professional Experience**

Cerby (2022-Present)

Senior SRE, Data Engineer, Software Engineer

- Architected and developed the application authorization (RBAC) system.
- Contributed to the design and development of numerous EPM features including Teams, Secrets, Collections, and Partnerships.
- Designed and developed a global message bus system for the platform.
- Created the Zero-knowledge and local-encryption architectures.

Wizeline (2020-Present)

Cloud Operations Discipline Lead / Engineering Manager

- Set the direction for the SRE discipline by establishing OKRs, SRE Communities.
- Improved the SRE discipline through coaching, mentoring, and initiating show-and-tell initiatives.
- Grew the SRE and cloud organization through hiring, training, and publishing articles (8x growth).
- Improved employee engagement.
- Managed a multi-disciplinary team of up to 24 engineers.

#### Wizeline (2019-Present)

Senior Staff SRE / DevOps

- Led the architecture and development of the next-gen data platform initiative for a FinTech client.
- Provided valuable guidance and input to multiple clients and projects.
- Led the team to achieve AWS DevOps-competence.

#### **Wizeline** (2017-2019)

Senior Site Reliability Engineer / DevOps Engineer

- Managed cloud environments for various company and customer projects.
- Enabled development teams to deploy releases following CI/CD practices.
- Designed, planned, and implemented cloud solution architectures for web and data services.
- Monitored and improved DevOps metrics.
- Led SRE for the internal bots platform and other projects.
- Conducted talks about DevOps practices, containerization, and CI/CD practices.
- Prepared the team and infrastructure to successfully obtain a SOC2 certification.

#### **Continental** (2016-2017)

Systems Test Manager

- Managed a team of 5+ engineers across 4 simultaneous projects.
- Implemented both traditional and Kanban methodologies for project planning, monitoring, controlling, and risk assessment.
- Participated actively and collaborated globally within the test manager community.

#### **Continental** (2014-2017)

Test Automation Engineer

- Created the architecture and implemented the testing tool-chain and framework for the test department, catering to embedded systems.
- Set up and managed Linux application servers for the QA department, including web applications, databases, GitLab, Nginx, RESTful APIs.
- Served as the go-to person for programming and automation solutions.
- Developed tooling applications for testing support using Ruby, Python, and Java (Backend and libraries).

- Worked with the Tire Pressure Monitoring System (TPMS) algorithms and functions, the PASE system, and computer vision algorithms.
- Designed and automated generic test specs for multiple functionalities and platforms.

#### **AppCo (Startup)** (2015-2017)

Lead Software Architect

- Led a team of 5 engineers.
- Architected and designed software applications using Ruby on Rails, Android, Sinatra, NodeJS.
- Conducted analysis, evaluation, and selection of development technologies.
- Developed web and mobile applications.
- Integrated with third-party services, such as Facebook, Google, Paypal, Conekta, Wordpress.
- Automated deployment and provisioning.

#### **Interactive Cozumel** (2013-2014)

Software Engineer

## **Education**

#### The Institute of Technology at Linköping University (2009-2013)

Bachelor's degree, Mechatronics, Robotics, and Automation Engineering

- Completed courses in Signal Processing, Advanced Control, Machine Learning, Advanced Mathematics.
- Participated in projects involving Machine Learning, DSP, Sensor Fusion Algorithms, and Digital Filters.

#### Instituto Tecnológico y de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey / ITESM (2009-2013)

Bachelor's degree, Mechatronics, Robotics, and Automation Engineering

### **Additional Notes: Results**

As an SRE Engineering Manager, I always provided valuable and prompt feedback to all the Engineers, understood and help them grow in their career and align them with the Discipline and company goals, resulting in a timespan of 1.5 years: a high performing team, where everyone has a mentor or a mentee, 5 promotions (approved by a committee), 5 projects with long recurring renovations, 70% of the team participation in Hiring initiatives, more than 65% of the team certified in either AWS, GCP, Terraform, k8s, and 5 SRE community champions.

The data-platform created for the FinTech customer improved the data team capabilities (CDC, parallel-compute, site-to-site VPN tunnels, schema-on-read, SFTP-to-S3), scalability, performance, and compliance. It went from a brittle, manual, and GUI-based flow to a fully compliant CI/CD process to introduce changes, to the infrastructure, data models, and DAGs. New database integrations improved from spending 3+days per table to be able to integrate a whole schema in 1 hour.

Other important initiatives for the FinTech customer included:

- Defining the AWS permissions strategy and implementing an Okta-AWS permissions and authentication system impacting how the whole company authenticated to AWS resulting in a more efficient approval and permissions assignment process (less than a day from weeks), and auditable file of all roles and permissions, a generators and configuration strategy to manager permissions complexity and enable composability.
- Refactoring some of the data-intensive and ML microservices to enable extensibility, some of these services were migrated from Scala and JavaScript to python to leverage the team skills. The refactored services have a 90%+ coverage, capability for A/B testing, observable, documented, and ETLed.
- Smaller initiatives included the discovery and PoC of a no-code/low-code solution in track to improve the experience and efficiency of the operation teams. Automated CD pipelines for the legacy infrastructure as code. Helped in the migration of a monolith to Kubernetes. Defined a strategy and automation to manage kubernetes manifests with Jsonnet, resulting in DRY and extensible configurations. Provided valuable input for the kops to EKS migration.

## **Additional Notes: Learning**

On the technical side, some of the things I have learned in the last year are:

- Clojure, to be exposed to different programming perspectives and practice functional programming. Read the book Clojure Applied.
- Snowflake, DBT, DVC, SageMaker I needed to get familiar with some of these technologies to have a better
  understanding and provide a better recommendation to the data team. I participated in a hackathon
  where we used DVC to demonstrate how can we ensure model reproducibility, compliance, and do an ML
  pipeline.
- GraphQL
- Currently reading Patterns of Enterprise Application Architecture by Martin Fowler
- Also read: Software Design Decoded, Engineering Software Products for a refresher

On the leadership and management side, read and applied some books:

- Radical Candor by Kim Scott
- The Score Takes Care of Itself by Bill Walsh
- Principles by Ray Dalio
- Infonomics by Douglas B. Laney

## **Additional Notes: Articles**

- How to ensure DevOps practices in a project
- A day in the life: What does a site reliability engineer do?